Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're gonna be learning about
the diatomic elements and exactly what
are they and how they bond together.
So the diatomic elements, these
are naturally occurring gases that
are exist in our everyday world.
And what these are, are different
elements that have the tendency
to want to bond to themselves.
So whenever we have these uh,
created during chemical reactions.
Or if we're trying to actually just
write these as they naturally are,
they're commonly found to be bound cells.
Meaning that for every one molecule
you're gonna have two individual atoms.
So what are they?
So the seven here, I like to call
'em by a bunch of different names.
Um, I like to call 'em a diatomic
seven, where you have hydrogen,
nitrogen, fluorine, oxygen,
iodine, fluorine, and bromine.
And all these different gases, like
I said, they bond to themselves.
So remembering these is vital to a general
chemistry student because they're used
so often, especially when you're learning
about chemical reactions and gas laws.
So how exactly do you remember these?
There's so many of them.
It can be very, very difficult to try
to commit any of this stuff to memory
'cause there's so much to remember.
So with everything, I love having
mnemonics to try to remember every
little piece of information that we have.
So for this, the phrase that you have
to remember is have no fear of ice
cold beer, which is always true no
matter what if you're in or outside.
If you're outside the class, that
isn't always gonna be a true statement.
So having no fear.
All right, so every first letter
here is one of your diatomic.
So have is hydrogen, no is nitrogen.
F for fluorine from fear of
is oxygen I, his iodine, and
C, chlorine, and B is bromine.
So if you remember, have
no fear of ice-cold beer.
You will never forget
your seven diatomics.
Write it down.
It's something that's gonna help you
remember these for your chemistry course.
So we're gonna go next is to
show why does this happen?
Why do they exist in this natural state?
Why are these gases so different?
Why do they bond to themselves, um,
and exist in this different way?
So we're gonna take a look at this.
The diatomic gases, they bond to
themselves and one of the things
we like to try to demonstrate
for chemistry students is that
they love to bond to themselves.
So what exactly how are they presented?
So many of these gases they're
referred to as when we're talking
about the diatomic version.
We like to say like hydrogen gas, oxygen
gas, fluorine gas, fluorine gas, and
that's referring to the molecular form.
So the word gas is extremely important.
Um, so for example, if I have hydrogen
gas, which is the first one, you
would see it written as H two and
generally in parentheses afterwards,
it is demonstrating a guess.
So that way you know what
you are working with.
Now let's talk about how it's bonded.
Well, it all has to do with the valence
electrons of all these different elements
and knowing how we can count and try
to understand how many do they have.
So the first one, hydrogen, right?
So if you think from your periodic
table, it is in column number one.
So it has a single valence
electron, meaning that if I were
to try to bring it near another
hydrogen, well if they were to bond.
Together we can see, hey, it
ends up filling the orbital for
each one of these hydrogens.
Remember, Hydrogen likes to
fulfill the duet rule, meaning
it only needs two electrons in
order for it to be fully happy.
So the hydrogen on the left has two
electrons, and then the hydrogen
on the right has two electrons.
So we have an even covalent
sharing between these two.
Okay.
So, and that's what's
most important, right?
It's fulfilling its outermost layer.
That is the ultimate goal.
So now there are elements, so
if I wanna start with the first
one, right, which is fluorine.
Well, we can think, all right.
How many valence electrons
does any of the halogens have?
Well, all of them have seven
valence electrons around them.
And that's some from counting
the columns of the periodic
table, you can get that number.
If we were to draw all those
little dots around fluorine, around
both of 'em, we'll line up the
single.next to its other species.
And one thing we're gonna see is, hey,
if this forms a single bond between
them, it's sharing two electrons between
both of 'em, meaning that we have a
total of eight on one side the other.
So that's one of the most
important things as we're seeing.
We have that equal sharing from
both sides and they both have
eight valence electrons now.
And it's so satisfying the octet.
And we can do this for any
of these species, right?
So if I pick another one, let's
say if I do chlorine, for example,
and we want to show this one, this
would be the exact same thing.
'cause it also has
seven valence electrons.
We can show a single bond around
it to help illustrate that this.
Has its complete octet, just like so.
All right, so all of the halogens,
they make one single bond and they
are able to satisfy their ho octet
covalently, which is the goal.
So this is why they, like,
they exist as diatomics.
It's really easy for them.
They can bond with their, their op,
their, their counterpart, and if it
fills their octet, it's stable, right?
So in order for these to happen, it helps.
Stabilize the structure, and
that's really important to realize.
Let's go onto the other ones,
which are a little harder.
So the last two, which is oxygen and
nitrogen are a little bit different.
Well, oxygen, how many valence
electrons does oxygen have?
And you can think about it for a
second and you'll realize, oh, it
has six valence Electrons around it.
So we're gonna draw six
dots around the structure.
What we're going to see here is like,
okay, well if I draw these six dots, well,
how many bonds does it need to form here?
Well, if I do the first one and do a
single bond, we're gonna see, wait a
minute, it doesn't quite have enough.
I'm to count all the dots for one of
these oxygens I have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, so we don't have eight at the moment.
So what do we need to do?
We need to make a complete another bond.
So we'll move through these dots,
make a double bond, and there we go.
We have now happy Octet,
which is showing okay.
The, the, the one on the right now has
eight valence electrons all being shared
with it, and the same thing on the left.
They both have a happy octet,
so we have a double bond.
This is oxygen gas.
Just like you're breathing
in right now, just like I'm
breathing into, so O2 gas, right?
As you can kind of think of what do you
breathe is O2, and it is something that
is a part, a vital part of our atmosphere.
Same thing with nitrogen, right?
We live in a nitrogen based
environment, so once again, we're
gonna write our Lewis structure.
We have five valence
electrons from nitrogen.
We're gonna write them all around.
And if you can kind of notice,
well, how many vacant dots
do I have around nitrogen?
Well, we have three lonely dots.
So if oxygen made a double bond, maybe
this can get your brain thinking of
what kind of bond I need to make here.
So notice how if I make one bond
right, we have a total of only six
electrons on the right hand side.
So what we need to do is
we need to share two more.
To make a total of, make a triple bond.
Okay?
So let's move all of our dots, make
a very, very happy structure, and
then this would be our first bond,
our second bond, and our third bond.
So, and as a result, if you kind of
think about, and we count all these so
we can, we can count and we can see that,
okay, we have, uh, 1, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
6, 7, 8, all of our valence
electrons are taken care of.
We have all of them here.
We have a complete valence level,
and so this is showing a perfect
structure using a triple bond.
And this is one of the reasons
why nitrogen is so stable within
our atmosphere, is typically
something that does not readily
react, and that's because it's very
difficult to break a triple bond.
It's one of the strongest
bonds you can have.
It's very strong and that is
how nitrogen naturally exists.
So these have been the seven
diatomics, as I mentioned before.
Just always kind of keep remembering,
is have no fear of ice cold beer
and you'll be re able to remember
all of your diatomics moving
forward in your chemistry course.
So this has been Dr.
Dan, thank you so much for Li
for listening and just remember,
have no fear of ice Cold beer.
I'll see you all later.
Bye now.